Fred Conley Collection
Fred Conley Collection
1939-1990
Conley, Fred (Fay Oliver)
.25 linear ft. (oversize flat box)
Clippings, memorabilia, photographs of the American plastics pioneer.
4072972
Biographical History
Fred (Fay Oliver) Conley (1899-1981) was an American plastics and automotive engineer.
A descendant of one of the oldest families in the country, Conley's ancestors can be traced back to Mayflower immigrants in 1620. He was the founder, first president and distinguished member of the Society of Plastic Engineers, a charter member of the Plastic Pioneers Association, and a senior member of the Engineering Society of Detroit. He assisted Louis Chevrolet with the first production model of the Chevrolet car, and was a distinguished member of the Automotive Old Timers. According to the Plastics Hall of Fame website, "He is credited with developing several plastics "firsts" in the automotive industry, such as a cowl ventilator and a patented interior sun visor. In 1932, he was instrumental in designing and developing a small portable radio cabinet -- reputedly the first plastics cabinet of its kind. "
Genealogy was his principal hobby and he successfully traced his ancestry back to Charlemagne. He was a member of the Sons of the American Revolution and other automotive, genealogical and hereditary societies, as well as benevolent clubs such as the Boys Club of Detroit, Elks Club, etc. He wasand his wife Polly had no children. [Adapted from Conley's obituary in the Kalamazoo Gazette, 14 Oct 1981]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Fred Conley Collection consists of biographical material, memorabilia, and miscellanea.
Biographical material consists of two biographical sketches, one published and one a typescript.
Memorabilia contains awards and certificates, many of which are related to the Conley family genealogy (e.g., Sons of the American Revolution). There are also a few photographs of Conley.
Miscellaneous material includes a small plastic artifact manufactured by Makalot Corp. and assorted printed material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type of material.
Related Material
has a number of collections relating to plastics and plastics history; please see for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Conley, Fred (Fay Oliver); Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Society of Plastics Engineers.; Plastics news.; Plastics industry and trade -- Technological innovations.; Plastics industry and trade -- History.; Plastics -- Research.; Awards.; Certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Engineers.; Businessmen.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gerald Young, 2013.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical sketches, 1960; undated; two biographical sketches of Conley, one from Colonial Families of the Americas and the other a typewritten manuscript, possibly by Conley himself. (Oversize 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards and honors, 1939-1978; 1990,; undated; wide variety, ranging from a certificate appreciation from the War Department to membership in the Descendants of the Knights of the Order of the Garter; the 1990 award was made posthumously (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings about, 1992; includes May 4 issue of Plastics News celebrating the 50th anniversary of the Society of Plastics Engineers (Oversize 1)
  - Photographs, 1949; 1977,; undated; candid photo, formal portrait photo, photo of framed painting of Conley; also includes business card from Conley's first business venture, "The F. Conley Co." (Oversize 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Artifact, undated; two small pieces resembling a tiny dish and saucer, labeled "One of the first items made of plastics, made by Makalot Corp. (Mac Makeever)" (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings, 1969; undated; includes lengthy article on radio personality Eddie Guest, who was a friend of Conley's; front page is annotated by Polly Conley (Oversize 1)
  - Printed material, undated; pamphlet on Arlington National Cemetery; "Statement of Principles by the Plastics Industry" (Oversize 1)